<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">37351</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2105-2-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-2-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The relationship between the L1 and L2 domains of the insulin and epidermal growth factor receptors and leucine-rich repeat modules</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>Colin W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>Colin.Ward@hsn.csiro.au</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>Thomas PJ</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>Tom.Garrett@hsn.csiro.au</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>CSIRO Health Sciences and Nutrition, 343 Royal Parade Parkville, Victoria 3052, Australia</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Walter and Elisa Hall Institute, Royal Melbourne Hospital, Parkville, Victoria 3052, Australia</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Cooperative Research Centre for Cellular Growth Factors, Royal Melbourne Hospital, Parkville, Victoria, 3050, Australia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2001</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2105/2/4"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2001</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2001 Ward and Garrett; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ward and Garrett; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Leucine-rich repeats are one of the more common modules found in proteins. The leucine-rich repeat consensus motif is LxxLxLxxNxLxxLxxLxxLxx- where the first 11&#x02013;12 residues are highly conserved and the remainder of the repeat can vary in size Leucine-rich repeat proteins have been subdivided into seven subfamilies, none of which include members of the epidermal growth factor receptor or insulin receptor families despite the similarity between the 3D structure of the L domains of the type I insulin-like growth factor receptor and some leucine-rich repeat proteins.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Here we have used profile searches and multiple sequence alignments to identify the repeat motif Ixx-LxIxx-Nx-Lxx-Lxx-Lxx-Lxx- in the L1 and L2 domains of the insulin receptor and epidermal growth factor receptors. These analyses were aided by reference to the known three dimensional structures of the insulin-like growth factor type I receptor L domains and two members of the leucine rich repeat family, porcine ribonuclease inhibitor and internalin 1B. Pectate lyase, another beta helix protein, can also be seen to contain the sequence motif and much of the structural features characteristic of leucine-rich repeat proteins, despite the existence of major insertions in some of its repeats.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Multiple sequence alignments and comparisons of the 3D structures has shown that right-handed beta helix proteins such as pectate lyase and the L domains of members of the insulin receptor and epidermal growth factor receptor families, are members of the leucine-rich repeat superfamily.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Many proteins have a modular architecture and are composed of a number of different, sometimes repeated structural units [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The four most common modules found in the extracellular regions of proteins are immunoglobulin (Ig) domains, epidermal growth factor (EGF)-like repeats, fibronectin type 3 (Fn3) modules and leucine-rich repeats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Two of these, Fn3 modules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] and EGF-like repeats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], have been identified in members of the insulin receptor (IR) family.</p><p>There is some evidence to suggest that the L domains of the IR and EGFR families are leucine-rich repeats. At 10&#x02013;16%, leucine is the most common residue in these domains. Furthermore, the 3D structure of the L1/cys-rich/L2 fragment of the IGF-1R showed that the L domains were single-stranded right-handed &#x003b2;-helices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] with structural similarities to pectate lyase, a right-handed beta helix protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and the ribonuclease inhibitor, a right-handed beta-alpha superhelix protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Ribonuclease inhibitor (RI) is recognised as a member of the superfamily of leucine-rich repeat proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] while pectate lyase is not, although similarities in the sequence patterns and 3D structures of pectate lyase and RI have been noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The IGF-1R is listed as a leucine-rich repeat protein in the SCOP database <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scop.mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk/scop/"/> but not in any of the annotated sequence databases such as SwissProt <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://srs.ebi.ac.uk/"/> or SMART <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/index.shtml"/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]). Similarly, none of the other L-domain containing proteins from the IR or EGFR families are listed as leucine-rich repeats in these data bases or in a recent summary of the complete protein tyrosine kinase family present in the human genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><p>The superfamily of leucine-rich repeat proteins has been subdivided into six subfamilies termed: typical, RI-like, CC (cysteine-containing), PS (plant specific), SD22-like and bacterial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. These subfamilies are characterised by different lengths and consensus sequences of the repeats (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The bulk of the LRRs have repeats of 22&#x02013;25 amino acid residues while RI, with its alternating repeats of 28 to 29 residues, is considered somewhat atypical [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. The family has been expanded further to include the small proteoglycans, which were shown to consist of different combinations of two types of LRRs of 21 (S-type) and 26 (T-type) amino acid residues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. The LRR consensus sequence is LxxLxLxxNx-Lxx-Lxx-Lxx-Lxx- (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) where the first 11&#x02013;12 residues are highly conserved and the remainder of the repeat can vary in size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Some repeats have C instead of N at the 4<sup>th</sup> highly conserved position and I, V, M, F, Y, A or C at the positions denoted by L in the above consensus (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of repeat motifs in IR and EGFR family L domains with the sequence motifs of LRR subfamilies. The motifs for LRR_Typical, LRR_PS type, LRR_bacterial type, LRR_SD22-like, LRR_CC type, LRR_R1 type-a, LRR_R1 type-b are based on [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], the motifs for the S and T type repeats of small proteoglycans (LRR_PGC) are from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. The size of the repeat can vary by insertions at the positions denoted by the dashes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Also shown is a consensus motif for the pectate lyase superfamily based on the alignments in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-2-4-1"/></fig><p>In view of this variation in sequence motifs among LRR proteins, the sequences of the L1 and L2 domains of members of the IR and EGFR families were re-examined. The LRR motif is difficult to detect when examining a single sequence, but becomes more readily recognisable when multiple sequence alignments are analysed. The identification of such conserved sequence motifs was greatly aided by the availability of the 3D structures of the IGF-1R L1 and L2 domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], pectate lyase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and the known LRR proteins RI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and internalin 1B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The data indicate that pectate lyase and the L domains of members of the IR and EGFR families should be included in the expanding family of LRR proteins</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Preliminary analyses of the SwissProt data base using profiles based on alignments of single (Prf1) or double LRR repeats (Prf2) failed to score members of the IR or EGFR families in the first 500 ranked scores. However searches with Prf-4 (based on four tandem repeats), ranked IR family members at positions 234 (INSR_RAT), 245 (INSR_MOUSE), 262 (IG1R_RAT) and 478 (IG1R_HUMAN) and EGFR family members at 146 (LT23_CAEEL), 174 (EGFR_MOUSE), 448 (EGFR_HUMAN) and 457 (EGFR_CHICK). The alignments with the mouse, human and chick EGFRs were to residues equivalent to 363&#x02013;452 in the L2 domain of EGFR_human. In contrast, the alignments with the other sequences were to regions in the cytoplasmic domain. When the analyses were restricted to the receptor ectodomains, the alignments were to sequences in the L1 or L2 domains. Examples are: Prf-1 with residues 1&#x02013;28, Prf-2 with residues 10&#x02013;78 and Prf-4 with residues 46&#x02013;153 in the human insulin receptor. An alternative approach, using a profile generated from the alignment of the L1 domains of 13 members of the IR family (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) was also encouraging as it ranked four known LRR proteins in the next 11 hits after the 26 known members of the IR or EGFR families. These were repeats 8&#x02013;14 (residues 295&#x02013;450) of ESA8_TRYEQ (ranked 28<sup>th</sup>) and ESA8_TRYBB (ranked 30<sup>th</sup>), and repeats 1&#x02013;5 (residues 28&#x02013;177) of TSHR_MOUSE (ranked 35<sup>th</sup>) and TSHR_RAT (ranked 37<sup>th</sup>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Leucine-rich repeats in the L1 and L2 domain of members of the insulin receptor family. The sequences were sourced from SwissProt except for IR_CAEEL which is GENBANK:AF012437. Residues equivalent to conserved positions 1 to 8 in the sequence motif LxxLxLxxNxLxxLxxLxxLxx are shaded. The INSR_MOUSE is not shown as it differs from INSR_RAT at only S139Y in the 6<sup>th</sup> repeat of the L1 domain and S415N in the 4<sup>th</sup> repeat of the L2 domain, positions that are not conserved in the LRR motif.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-2-4-2"/></fig><p>However, in both approaches, the repeating units in the L1 and L2 domains, known from the 3D structure of IGF-1R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], did not align exactly with the repeating units in the LRR proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] or the LRR protein profiles (see Methods). The presence of insertions in some regions of the IR or EGFR proteins tended to confound the profile alignments. Consequently, the nature of the repeating sequence motifs in the L1 and L2 domains of the IR and EGFR families were examined manually using the 3D structure of the L1 and L2 domains of IGF-1R as a guide to adjust the alignments obtained from the profile analyses.</p><p>The consensus sequences for the six LRR protein subfamilies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. The sizes of the repeating units vary from 22&#x02013;31 with eight highly conserved positions, numbered 1 to 8 in Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. Conserved position 4 usually contains N or C but sometimes S, T, P, Q or A. The other 7 highly conserved positions are generally L but frequently contain alternative non-polar residues such as I, V, M, C, A, F, or Y, particularly in some LRR subfamilies. Also included are the type S and type T LRRs from the small proteoglycans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. The repeating motifs have been arranged in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> so that they all begin with the 11-residue stretch LxxLxLxxNxL which contains the highly conserved positions 1 to 5. This motif corresponds to a linear central sequence with two half turns at either end [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Deletions and/or insertions, particularly in the C-terminal portion of the repeats (after conserved positions 5, 6, 7 and 8) account for the size differences seen between different LRR protein members.</p><p>The repeat sequences in members of the IR family that correspond to the six turns of the parallel beta helix of the L1 and L2 domains of IGF-1R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. The corresponding predicted repeats for members of the EGFR family are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>. LRR-like motifs are most readily identified in the 4<sup>th</sup> and 5<sup>th</sup> repeats in the IR family L1 and EGFR family L2 domains and in the 3<sup>rd</sup>, 4<sup>th</sup> and 5<sup>th</sup> repeats of the IR family L2 and EGFR family L1 domains. The size of these repeats (22&#x02013;30 residues) is similar to the range found in other LRRs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The 4<sup>th</sup> repeat in the L1 and L2 domains of the IR family contain an insert of 7&#x02013;8 residues between conserved positions 1 and 2 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), which appears as an extra loop in the 3D structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The 4<sup>th</sup> repeats of the majority of the EGFR L1 and L2 domains show similar inserts of 6&#x02013;7 residues in this region, with the EGFR from <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> (SMEGFRA) and <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (TOP_DROME) having inserts of 11 and 13 residues respectively (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Variable sized insertions are also seen in some (or all) of the 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> repeats of the IR and EGFR L1 domains and the 1<sup>st</sup>, 2<sup>nd</sup> and 6<sup>th</sup> repeats of the IR and EGFR family L2 domains.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Leucine-rich repeats in the L1 and L2 domains of members of the epidermal growth factor receptor family. The sequences were sourced from SwissProt except for SMEGFRA which is from EMBL and CVULET23 which is from GENBANK. Residues equivalent to conserved positions 1 to 8 in the sequence motif LxxLxLxxNxLxxLxxLxxLxx are shaded.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-2-4-3"/></fig><p>The nature of the residues in the eight highly conserved positions of the LRR-like repeats in the L domains of IR and EGFR are summarised in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. The most commonly found residues in the L domains of the IR and EGFR families are: isoleucine at positions 1 and 3; asparagine at position 4; and leucine at positions 2, 5, 6, 7 and 8. However other non-polar residues, particularly valine, phenylalanine and cysteine, occur in positions 1&#x02013;3 and 5&#x02013;8 in some sequences (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The most common alternatives to asparagine at the 4<sup>th</sup> conserved position are valine, methionine, serine and tryptophan (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Frequency of occurrence of amino acid residues in the eight conserved positions of the LRR-like motifs in the L domains of the IR and EGFR families</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Residue</td><td align="center" colspan="8">IR Family (L1 + L2)</td><td align="center" colspan="8">EGFR Family (L1 + L2)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="8"><hr></hr></td><td colspan="8"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center">2<sup>nd</sup></td><td align="center">3<sup>rd</sup></td><td align="center">4<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">5<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">6<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">7<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">8<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center">2<sup>nd</sup></td><td align="center">3<sup>rd</sup></td><td align="center">4<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">5<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">6<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">7<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center">8<sup>th</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">H</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">K</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">R</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">D</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">E</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">N</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center"><bold>68</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center"><bold>61</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Q</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">S</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">T</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center">P</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">G</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">V</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">I</td><td align="center"><bold>91</bold></td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center"><bold>95</bold></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center"><bold>57</bold></td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center"><bold>78</bold></td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">9</td></tr><tr><td align="center">L</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center"><bold>70</bold></td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center"><bold>85</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>80</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>51</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>64</bold></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center"><bold>70</bold></td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center"><bold>57</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>69</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>46</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>53</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">M</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">C</td><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td></td><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">24</td></tr><tr><td align="center">F</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">39</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">28</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Y</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">W</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td></td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td></td><td align="center">23</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Calculated from conserved positions indicated in Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The locations of the eight conserved residues in the 3D structure of IGF-1R L1 domain have been compared with the location of the equivalent residues in the 3D structures of the known LRR proteins porcine RI and internalin 1B. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, the 3D structures of the first part of the repeat (LxxLxLxxNx) are very similar in each of these proteins (&#x003b2;-strand flanked by two half turns), while the structures of the remainder of the repeats are more variable. This is despite the size variability of the sequence patterns seen in some of the repeats in the L domains of the IGF-1R and the more frequent occurrence of non-L residues at highly conserved positions 1&#x02013;3 and 5&#x02013;8.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the location of conserved motif residues in the 3D structures of IGF-1R L1 domain and other LRR and &#x003b2;-helix proteins. The 3D structures are <italic>a</italic> human, IG1R fragment (PDB: 1IGR, residues 50&#x02013;143), <italic>b,</italic> internalin 1B from <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> (PDB: 1D0B, residues 143&#x02013;241),<italic>c,</italic> porcine ribonuclease inhibitor (PDB:2BNH, residues 24&#x02013;148) and <italic>d,</italic> pectate lyase C from <italic>Erwinia chrysanthemi</italic> (PDB:1PEC, residues 86&#x02013;245). Residues equivalent to conserved positions 1 to 8 in the sequence motif LxxLxLxxNxLxxLxxLxxLxx are colour coded as follows: position 1: blue; positions 2 &#x00026; 3: green; position 4: yellow; positions 5 &#x02013; 8: red.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-2-4-4"/></fig><p>The pectate lyase family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] shows even greater variability, with large insertions in some repeats corresponding to loops overlaying the parallel beta helix core (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). As for other LRRs, the most conserved residues include positions 2&#x02013;4, being two aliphatic side chains and the Asn ladder (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). However, at each of the 8 highly conserved positions, isoleucine or valine is preferred over leucine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. In positions 2 and 3 the frequency of I or V is greater than 60%. The features which set apart the pectate lyase repeat from that of other LRR families are an aromatic residue in position 5, extending the third &#x003b2;-strand and forming a bulge (<italic>top left</italic> in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Residues at positions 7 and 8 slide over to spatially overlap with positions 6 and 7 in other LRRs.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Structural repeats in the sequences of <italic>Erwinia chrysanthemi</italic> pectate lyase C (PEC, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]), <italic>Bacillus Subtilis</italic> pectate lyase (BN8, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]) and <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> pectin lyase B (QCX, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]). Alignment is based on a superposition of the three-dimentional structures, with residues in the sequence motif shaded. Charged residues (boxed) also form part of the motif but have either a compensating buried charge or are solvent exposed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-2-4-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>There is considerable interest in the structure of the L domains of the IR and EGFR families and their relationship with other proteins, because of their importance in ligand binding (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]). In this paper, evidence is presented to show that these L domains contain all of the features of leucine-rich repeats. Multiple sequence alignments, coupled with the 3 D structure of the L1 and L2 domains of the IGF-1R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], enabled the residues equivalent to the conserved residues in known LRR motifs, to be identified as summarised in Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>.</p><p>A variant of the motif LxxLxLxxNx-Lxx-Lxx-Lxx-Lxx- found in LRR proteins can be identified in the L1 and L2 domains of the IR and EGFR families, where I rather than L is the most common residue at positions 1 and 3. Other non-polar amino acids frequently occur in some positions (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), as found with other LRR proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. The L domains of the IR and EGFR families contain five full repeats with the 6<sup>th</sup> partially truncated. Some sequences have insertions between conserved positions 1 and 2 and 4 and 5 (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), which complicate the analysis. However the combination of examining multiple sequence alignments with the known 3D structure of the IGF-1R allowed the sequence motifs to be established.</p><p>Leucine rich repeat proteins are members of a broader class of proteins termed solenoid proteins, where the repeating structural units in the polypeptide chain form a continuous superhelix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Solenoid proteins, including LRRs, show the simplest relationship between sequence and structure, compared to the more complicated folds of globular proteins. Thus recognition of such motifs can provide valuable insights into the predicted structure of such protein domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The most conserved structural feature of LRRs is the LxxLxLxxNx region, while the remainder of the repeat can differ dramatically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] as illustrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>. The central sequence xLxLx in this region of the repeat forms a &#x003b2;-strand with successive repeats of this &#x003b2;-strand forming a parallel &#x003b2;-sheet on one side of the LRR module. This corresponds to the second &#x003b2;-sheet in the L domains of the IGF-1R, which is the structural counterpart of the &#x003b2;-sheet that forms the inner face of RI and internalin (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). This face is involved in protein-protein interactions in RI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], U2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] and the IR family (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]).</p><p>As shown in Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, the first region of the repeat LxxLxLxxNx in RI, internalin, the IGF-1R L domains and pectate lyase all adopt similar structural folds, while the remainder of the repeats are highly variable. Most of the repeats in the IR and EGFR L domains are between 21 and 30 residues, within the range commonly found in other LRRs. The inserts are accommodated as loops which do not, or are unlikely to, perturb the core structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Three of the repeats in pectate lyase have large inserts of 11&#x02013;17 residues between the 6<sup>th</sup> and 7<sup>th</sup> conserved position (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). The major difference between the 3D structures of RI and internalin versus the L domains of IGF-1R is the absence of the repetitive helix on the opposite face to the canonical &#x003b2;-sheet in the IGF-1R L domains and thus a lack of curvature although the L domains of IGF-1R are capped by &#x003b1;-helices at the N-terminal end and to a lesser extent at the C-terminus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>The existence of repeats in the L domains of IR and EGFR was first reported by Bajaj et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] who described five repeats in the region equivalent to 1&#x02013;119 in human IR. The subsequent 3D structure determination of the two L domains in the IGF-1R showed that they each contain five full and one partial repeat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Here we have shown, using a combination of sequence analyses and 3D structure comparisons, that variations of the repeating motif typical of LRRs is present in the L domains of members of the IR and EGFR subfamilies and in &#x003b2;-helix proteins. This motif is not obvious, is difficult to detect with sequence analysis programs and has not been described previously. Comparison of the 3D structure of these domains with other protein structures showed that L domains matched equally well to the pectate lyase family and LRRs such as porcine ribonuclease inhibitor. We conclude that these three groups should be considered part of the same LRR superfamily. In the IR and EGFR subfamilies, isoleucine (or valine) is preferred over leucine at some positions of the repeat while in &#x003b2;-helix proteins isoleucine or valine (or occasionally phenylalanine) are always preferred over leucine.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Multiple Sequence Analysis</title><p>The sequence analysis programs used were from the sequence analysis software package of the Genetics Computer Group of the University of Wisconsin, Biotechnology Centre, Madison, Wisconsin, USA. Files of individual proteins were edited using the Seqed program and aligned using Pileup. Final adjustment to these alignments were made manually as required using Lineup. Profiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] were generated from these aligned sequences using ProfileMake. The SwissProt database was probed using ProfileSearch and the alignments displayed with ProfileSegments. Specific sequences were analysed using Gap or ProfileGap. Gap weight and Length weight penalties used were 3.0 and 0.3 respectively unless stated otherwise.</p><p>The proteins used to generate these profiles, were the chondroadherin precursor (CHAD_BOVIN, 10 LRRs), platelet glycoprotein 1B alpha chain precursor (GPBA_MOUSE, 8 LRRs), the bone proteoglycan 2 precursor (PGS2_RABIT, 10 LRRs) and the putative receptor protein tyrosine kinase from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (TMK1_ARATH, 8 LRRs). Three profiles were generated: Prf-1 based on the alignment of the 38 single LRRs in these four proteins; Prf-2 based on the alignment of the 19 tandem repeats of two LRRs from these four proteins and Prf-4 which was generated from the alignment of eight sequences, each containing four LRRs in tandem. The fragments from CHAD_BOVIN and PGS2_RABIT used in Prf-4 corresponded to repeats 1&#x02013;4 and 7&#x02013;10.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>3D, three dimensional; EGF, epidermal growth factor, EGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor, Fn3, fibronectin type 3; IR, insulin receptor; IGF-1, insulin-like growth factor 1; IGF-1R, the type I insulin-like growth factor receptor; IRR, insulin receptor related receptor; LRR, leucine-rich repeat; RI, ribonuclease inhibitor; SCOP, structural comparison of proteins; SMART, simple modular architecture research tool.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mobile modules and motifs.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0959-440X(92)90233-W</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and distribution of modules in extracellular proteins.</article-title><source>Quart Rev Biophys</source><year>1996</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>167</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Bryan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cogswell</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Neubauer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokop</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinosa III</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Beau</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Earp</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>axl</italic>, a transforming gene isolated from primary human myeloid leukemia cells, encodes a novel receptor tyrosine kinase.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>5016</fpage><lpage>5031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1656220</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulhern</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A third fibronectin type-3 domain in the insulin-family receptors.</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9868364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0968-0004(98)01288-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marino-Buslje</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Blundell</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A third fibronectin type 3 domain in the extracellular region of the insulin receptor family.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>441</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9883910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(98)01509-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Members of the insulin receptor family contain three fibronectin type 3 domains.</article-title><source>Growth Factors</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10427505</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoyne</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Flegg</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin and epidermal growth factor receptors contain the cysteine repeat motif found in the tumour necrosis factor receptor.</article-title><source>Proteins: Struct Funct Genet</source><year>1995</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7567962</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>TPJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McKern</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frenkel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovrecz</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Elleman</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure of the first three domains of the type 1 insulin-like growth factor receptor.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>394</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9690478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/28668</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>TPJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McKern</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the insulin receptor family: unexpected relationships with other proteins.</article-title><source>Today's Life Sciences</source><year>1999</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Epa</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and function of the type I insulin-like growth factor receptor.</article-title><source>Cell Molec Life Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1050</fpage><lpage>1093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10961344</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lietzke</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurnak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unusual structural features in the parallel beta-helix in pectate lyases.</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>1993</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8081738</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurnak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New domain motif: pectate lyase C, a secreted plant virulence factor.</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1993</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>1503</fpage><lpage>1507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8502994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisenhofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of porcine ribonuclease inhibitor, a protein with leucine repeats.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1993</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8264799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/366751a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisenhofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The leucine-rich repeat: a versatile binding motif.</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7817399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0968-0004(94)90090-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Deisenhofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteins with leucine-rich repeats.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7583641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0959-440X(95)80105-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kajava</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural diversity of leucine-rich repeat proteins.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9533877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1998.1643</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kajava</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>When protein folding is simplified to protein coiling: the continuum of solenoid protein structures.</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11050437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0968-0004(00)01667-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Copley</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SMART: a web-based tool for the study of genetically mobile domains.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.231</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S-F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protein tyrosine kinase family of the human genome.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>5548</fpage><lpage>5557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj/onc/120395710.1038/sj.onc.1203957</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kajava</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wodak</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling of the three-dimensional structure of proteins with typical leucine-rich repeats.</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>1995</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8535781</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohyanagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretsinger</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Super-motifs and evolution of tandem leucine-rich repeats within the small proteoglycans-biglycan, decorin, lumican, fibromodulin, PRELP, keratocan, osteoadherin, epiphycan, and osteoglycin.</article-title><source>Proteins: Struct Funct Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10656267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0134(20000201)38:2&#x0003c;210::AID-PROT9&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the InIB leucine-rich repeats, a domain that triggers host cell invasion by the bacterial pathogen <italic>L-monocytogenes</italic>.</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>1072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10635330</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smiley</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadnyk</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Myler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The trypanosome leucine repeat gene in the variant surface glycoprotein expression site encodes a putative metal-binding domain and a region resembling protein-binding domains of yeast, Drosophila, and mammalian proteins.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>6436</fpage><lpage>6444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2247064</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Heffron</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lietzky</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurnak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional implications for structure-based sequence alignment of proteins in the extracellular pectate lyase superfamily.</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7716248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.3.963</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurnak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The parallel &#x003b2; helix and other coiled folds.</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7896002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heffron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieber</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengaud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitali</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurnak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence profile of a parallel b helix in the pectate lyase superfamily.</article-title><source>J Struct Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9724624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jsbi.1998.3978</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lax</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Howk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Givol</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of the ligand binding site of EGF-receptor utilizing chimeric chicken/human receptor molecules.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1989</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2785915</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Odaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lax</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 40-kDa epidermal growth factor/transforming growth factor alpha-binding domain produced by limited proteolysis of the extracellular domain of the epidermal growth factor receptor.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>1976</fpage><lpage>1981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8420971</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the spliceosomal U2B"-U2A' protein complex bound to a fragment of U2 small nuclear RNA.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>394</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9716128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/29234</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bajaj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterfield</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blundell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the tertiary structure of the extracellular domains of the epidermal growth factor and insulin receptors.</article-title><source>BiochimBiophys Acta</source><year>1987</year><volume>916</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3676333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0167-4838(87)90112-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devereux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haeberli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Smithies</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive set of sequence analysis programs for the VAX.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1984</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6546423</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gribskov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luthy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profile analysis.</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1990</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2314273</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pickersgill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert-Baudouy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure of Bacillus subtilis pectate lyase in complex with calcium.</article-title><source>Nat Struct Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7634076</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vitali</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schick</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kester</surname><given-names>HCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurnak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The three-dimensional structure of Aspergillus niger pectin lyase B at 1.7 &#x000c5; resolution.</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9449837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.116.1.69</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


